<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The felicity of a Christian life by Hierome Savonarola.</title>
            <title>De simplicitate Christianae vitae. Liber 5. English</title>
            <author>Savonarola, Girolamo, 1452-1498.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7937</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13241959</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13241959</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98636</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62263)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98636)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 438:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The felicity of a Christian life by Hierome Savonarola.</title>
                  <title>De simplicitate Christianae vitae. Liber 5. English</title>
                  <author>Savonarola, Girolamo, 1452-1498.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: De simplicitate Christianae vitae.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>This work also appears, on reel 649:7, as the third title in: Five treatises, 1651 (Wing V456).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98636:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98636:1"/>
            <p>THE FELICITY OF A Chriſtian Life.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>angel</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>By <hi>Hierome Savonarola.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98636:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98636:2"/>
            <head>The Felicity of a CHRISTIAN LIFE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>I.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat among all Creatures of this world man onely worketh for ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain end.</hi> That onely thing we ſay <hi>worketh for its end,</hi> which deſigneth unto it ſelf ſome particular <hi>end</hi> or reaſon of its work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and for the gaining thereof uſeth convenient means. Now this being impoſſible to be done without diſcourſe of reaſon, and that being proper onely unto man, it followes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98636:3"/>that man onely can be ſaid proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>to work for ſome end:</hi> And that Bruit Creatures are rather <hi>Acted,</hi> that is, carried by a ſwing of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall propenſity, <hi>to their ſeverall ends,</hi> then that they <hi>act</hi> or move themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>II.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat there is ſom ultimate or laſt end of humane life.</hi> In all things which are eſſentially ordinate one to another, we ſee that the firſt and principall being removed, all the reſt which were ſubordinate unto it muſt faile: So the firſt mover or cauſe of all things being denyed, all inferiour Agents and ſecond cauſes muſt of neceſſity ceaſe. Now in all humane Actions there is a certain order obſervable, by which one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is ſubordinate and directed, as it were, unto another; as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98636:3"/>in the building of an houſe, wee provide ſtones in order to reare the walls, the walls we intend for the houſe-ſake, the houſe for our dwelling: But in things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that which firſt exciteth the mind of the Agent, and moves him to work is the end, or ayme which he deſireth to compaſs by duemeans; if therefore there were not ſome <hi>ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate or laſt end,</hi> beyond which nothing elſe could be intended or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, the appetite of man would never be fixed, but perpetually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring this thing for that things ſake, and that thing again for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo <hi>in infinitum:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it would alſo follow, that there could be no Terme or period of his Action, which were abſurd. Wee muſt therefore of neceſſity grant ſome <hi>ultimate or laſt end</hi> of the life of man, I mean which ſhall be ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and abſolutely ſuch, and from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98636:4"/>which man (who is truly maſter of his own Actions) ſhall alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>to work:</hi> and although it be not neceſſary, that at all times his mind be actually and diſtinctly upon that <hi>end,</hi> yet that habitually and virtual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſhould be, as upon the thing, which doth in the firſt place and more then any thing elſe move him to work: for ſo we ſee, all men are moved to do what they do, either to avoid miſery, or to procure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves happineſſe, for as much as all men have this general end, as it were, ingrafted into their minds; and the difference that is among them is not, whither they ſhould all deſire to be happy or no, but in what Thing True happineſſe doth conſiſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98636:4"/>
               <head>The <hi>III.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That mans happineſſe conſiſteth in the fruition or poſſeſsion of his laſt end.</hi> Happineſs is ſuch a perfect good, as doth abſolutely ſatisfie and fulfill the deſire of man: for as much as we count him onely happy, who both enjoyeth whatſoever he deſires, and can deſire nothing more. As on the other ſide, every thing when it attaineth its proper end, is reconed perfect, becauſe it doth all its other things onely in order to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>that;</hi> when therefore <hi>that</hi> is obtained, it hath nothing elſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, it is therefore <hi>then</hi> perfect: for that which is not perfect, is ſtil thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſtill ſeeking or deſiring to be perfected; But that which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be <hi>already</hi> perfect, muſt not in reaſon be ſuppoſed to deſire perfection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98636:5"/>
               <head>The <hi>IV.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAns happineſs conſiſteth not in any outward goods.</hi> By <hi>outward goods,</hi> we underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Riches, Honours Dignities, Power, &amp;c. in which we ſay <hi>The happineſs of man conſiſteth not.</hi> For proof whereof I could al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge an infinite number of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but the Thing it ſelf being ſo clear as it is, and acknowledged by all, I ſhall inſiſt onely upon ſome few. My firſt reaſon is, becauſe happineſs is the ſupream or chief good of man, which admitteth not the leaſt mixture or participation of evill, no more then the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of heat doth any degree of cold: Bleſſedneſs therefore cannot conſiſt in the fruition of <hi>ſuch goods,</hi> which (as continuall experience tells us) do admit variety of evils, not of fortune only or chance, but (which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98636:5"/>is worſt of all,) <hi>the evils of ſin:</hi> for ſo we ſee, very wicked men have their ſhare <hi>in theſe goods.</hi> Secondly, becauſe Bleſſedneſs is a <hi>Self-ſuffice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good,</hi> ſuch as once being had, no other content can be wanting; but we ſee, though a man be never ſo well provided of <hi>theſe goods,</hi> yet 'tis poſſible he may be ſtill in want of others no leſs neceſſary; as a rich man is not alwayes wiſe, nor a man of Honour healthfull. Thirdly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Bleſſedneſs is ſuch a perfect good Thing, that from it no evill can proceed, which is not true of Riches, Honours, Power, &amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by occaſion of them, through the envy indeed and malice of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers many miſchiefs do ariſe, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Parricides, Treaſons, &amp; what not? Fourthly, becauſe the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples which diſpoſe a man unto True happineſs are intrinſecall or from within him, it being the end
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98636:6"/>whereunto he is naturally ordained and fitted; But unto <hi>the goods</hi> wee ſpeak of, Riches, Honours, &amp;c. a man is rather diſpoſed by cauſes extrinſecall and from without him, yea many times, by meere chance, and therefore they are called com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Goods of Fortune: it is clear therefore, that in them Felicity can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſiſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>V.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That mans happineſſe conſiſteth not in the goods of the Body.</hi> By <hi>goods of the body</hi> we mean the life of man, Health, Beauty, Youth, Strength, Courage, and the like, in all or in any of which, it is manifeſt, true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe cannot conſiſt. Becauſe firſt, this body is not made for it ſelf, but for the ſoule; as the matter is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes for the forme, and not the forme for the matter. Therefore it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98636:6"/>is, that all <hi>goods</hi> belonging to the body, are ordained indeed for the ſoule as unto the proper end for which they are made. Beſides, ſhould the happineſſe of man be placed in ſuch <hi>goods</hi> as thoſe, this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity would follow, namely that many even Bruit Beaſts ſhould par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of happineſſe more then man; for certainly as to the fruition of ſuch bodily goods, there be many beaſts which do far excell man: as for example, in length of life the Elephant, in ſtrength and courage the Lyon, the Stag in ſwiftneſs, the Eagle in ſharp ſightedneſs, and in perfection and ſoundneſſe of health almoſt all of them; for experience tels us, what a number of helps and how much art is requiſite to ſupport this fraile carcaſe of ours, more then of any other kind of creatures; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'its impoſſible true felicity ſhould be found in <hi>it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98636:7"/>
               <head>The <hi>VI.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NEither doth it conſiſt in the goods, that is to ſay, in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures &amp; ſat is factions of the ſenſitive part of the ſoul.</hi> Every thing the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it approacheth to its proper end, the perfecter it growes (for its end is its perfection) if therefore Bleſſedneſs conſiſted in thoſe ſenſitive delights, A man ſhould become ſo much the more perfect, by how much he lived more ſenſually, and gave himſelf up to all kind of Luxury and voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; that is, he ſhould be ſo much the more a man, by how much he lived more like a beaſt: which is very abſurd. And ſo againe (as was touched in the precedent Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) Beaſts alſo would be found ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of happineſs, as well as men, yea rather of a more perfect happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs then man; for as much as they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98636:7"/>have no fear of death, no apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of future miſeries, no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, no feare of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no Lawes, no Shame, no repugnance of fleſh and ſpirit; in brief they have nothing, which can either abate the ſenſe, or reſtraine the uſe of their preſent pleaſures: if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Felicity of man did conſiſt in the pleaſures of ſenſe, we ſhould all deſire to be metamorphiz'd and become Beaſts: why? becauſe Beaſts (upon this ſuppoſition) are more happy then men. But this was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be abſurd before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>VII.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat the happineſs of man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in ſuch goods, as pertain unto the Intellectuall</hi> or ſuperiour <hi>part of the ſoule.</hi> For as the body is ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſoule, ſo of the ſoule the vegetative or loweſt part is ordained
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98636:8"/>for the Senſitive, and the Senſitive for the Intellectuall. Seeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the Intellect or Rationall part of the Soul, is (as it were) the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and the thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto both <hi>it,</hi> and alſo the inferiour parts of the ſoul be ſubordinate and directed: it is manifeſt, that in the <hi>Act</hi> or exerciſe of this Intellect, and in the <hi>goods,</hi> that is to ſay, in the perfections thereto properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing, the finall happineſſe of man doth conſiſt. Beſides, ſeeing that happineſſe belongs onely to a perfect man, and that the perfection of man as man, conſiſteth in ſuch goods as belong either to his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding or will; it is hence alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that in ſuch manner of goods as are Intellectuall and rationall, his proper happineſſe conſiſteth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98636:8"/>
               <head>The <hi>VIII.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>But yet this happineſſe of man doth not conſiſt in any created good, although intellectuall.</hi> For, as we ſaid before, Bleſſedneſſe is ſuch a perfect good, as doth totally ſatisfie or fulfill the appetite; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it could not be the <hi>ultimate or laſt end,</hi> ſuppoſing there remained any thing elſe further to be deſired. Now the object of the will, (that is, of the appetite of man as man) is <hi>good in its latitude,</hi> or the <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall good.</hi> For we find, that as the underſtanding of man comprehends an infinitie of particular <hi>verities;</hi> that is to ſay, it never comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth actually ſo many, but it is ſtill apt and capable to comprehend more ſucceſſively even <hi>in infinitum;</hi> ſo alſo we find, that the will of man is as able to deſire and effect an infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98636:9"/>of particular <hi>goods;</hi> that is to ſay, that <hi>it</hi> alſo never actually deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſo many, but it is ſtill ready to accept and embrace more, whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever offered, and this ſucceſſively <hi>in infinitum,</hi> and that therefore it can never be fully ſatisfied, untill it attains to ſome <hi>univerſall or infinite good;</hi> which is not to be found in any created Thing: for the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of every Thing created, is at beſt but derivative, particular, and finite; therefore in no <hi>created good</hi> can the Felicity of man conſiſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>IX.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the happineſſe of man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth ſolely in the contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fruition of God.</hi> We ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the underſtanding of man reſteth not, that is, is not ſatisfied in the knowledge of <hi>particular veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> nor his will in the fruition of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98636:9"/>
                  <hi>particular goods.</hi> The <hi>laſt end</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of them both muſt be <hi>Truth and Goodneſſe univerſall,</hi> or in its full latitude, which God onely is: therefore in the Contemplation and Fruition of God alone the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitude of man conſiſteth. Beſides, man being what he is, <hi>viz.</hi> a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture naturally deſirous to know, and that our knowledge of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular thing ſeems then to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, when we comprehend its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and true cauſe; hence it follows, that whenſoever we obſerve any thing <hi>to be,</hi> that is to ſay, any effect; we inſtantly, yea naturally deſire to know its cauſe, why, what, or whence it is. Now all things, beſide God, appear unto us, and in truth are, but <hi>effects</hi> of ſome other cauſe; and therefore, whatſoever a man knows beſide God, he knows it either per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly or imperfectly: if imperfectly, his deſire is never ſatisfied, untill he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98636:10"/>perfect knowledge thereof (for that is naturall, <hi>viz.</hi> for every thing that is imperfect to deſire perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) and ſeeing that Felicity, as we have ſaid, is the perfection of man, and the full ſatisfaction of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall appetite; it is manifeſt, that by ſuch imperfect knowledge of any thing he cannot become hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: But if he knows the thing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, ſuppoſe it be ſome one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, or many, yea perhaps all particular things that be, yet he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but apprehend them ſtill as <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects,</hi> that is, as depending (in their very beings) upon ſome other cauſe. Seeing therefore, as we ſaid, that man obſerving the effect, doth naturally deſire to know the cauſe; it is manifeſt, that this appetite of his cannot be compleatly ſatisfied with the knowledge even of all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular things that be, but ſtill it will be endeavouring and deſiring to ſee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98636:10"/>alſo the cauſe of them all; and that ſo much the more earneſtly, by how much it finds the effects themſelves to be more excellent; or that it ſelf apprehends them more perfectly: for ſo it is alwayes ſeen, that every naturall motion, the nearor it draws to its period or proper term, the ſtronger and ſtronger it grows. In the ſole knowledge therefore and fruition of God (who is the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall and firſt cauſe of all Things) doth mans Bleſſedneſſe conſiſt: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently well obſerved, <hi>Thou haſt made us O Lord</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>for thy ſelf, and our heart is reſtleſſe and unquiet, untill it findeth its repoſe in Thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>X.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That this Beatitude formally, and as it were in</hi> actu primo, <hi>conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98636:11"/>in the underſtanding or ſeeing of God, as he is; but exercitatively, operatively, and as in</hi> actu ſecundo, <hi>in the will, or in that ineffable plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight which is enjoyed by the knowledge and contemplaton of him.</hi> The Act of the will alwayes preſuppoſeth the Act of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, becauſe the object thereof is alwayes ſome <hi>known or imaginary good.</hi> Seeing therefore that Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude formally and in its own nature is nothing elſe but the attaining of our laſt end, as ſoon as ever a man attains that he is happy. But man attaineth his laſt end (which is God) ſo ſoon as ever he <hi>ſees,</hi> that is, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly knows him. Therefore <hi>in the knowledge,</hi> and <hi>by the knowledge</hi> of his laſt end, man becomes <hi>eſſentially</hi> happy. But yet becauſe this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or contemplation of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty is inſeparably accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a certain infinite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98636:11"/>joy or pleaſure conceived up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſight, and by which the ſight or contemplation it ſelf ſeems to be perfected, therfore we ſay that in regard of <hi>operation</hi> or the exerciſe of Beatitude, that it is compleated in the <hi>will,</hi> which with an infinite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light doth embrace that <hi>good ſight,</hi> and conſent to be abſorpt and drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the glorious Abyſs thereof to all Eternity. As in like manner we ſay of man, that he conſiſts <hi>eſſentially</hi> in the union of a rationall Soul with the body, but yet that he is perfected in regard of operations by ſuch acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents as do either neceſſarily or contingently follow that union: to w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſenſe the Philoſopher alſo ſaith, <hi>Delight hath the ſame relation to Felicity, which Beauty hath to youth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98636:12"/>
               <head>The <hi>XI.</hi> Concluſion</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That perfect Bleſſedneſſe cannot be attained in this life.</hi> Firſt, becauſe in this life we have no immediate knowledge of God, we ſee him not but by and through the creatures, and as it were in ſuch a glaſſe, as the Phantaſie or ſome inferiour fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of our ſoul is able to preſent unto us: which manner of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge being ſo imperfect, the ſoul of man ſinds no ſatisfaction therein, that is to ſay, no Beatitude, no <hi>full content.</hi> Secondly, becauſe, as <hi>Boe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſaith, Bleſſedneſſe is a ſtate conſummate, or perfected with a concurrence of <hi>all good;</hi> but in this mortall life, there never was ſeen, (nor ever ſhall be) ſuch a generall confluence of <hi>All Good Things</hi> upon any one man, as that nothing ſhould be wanting either to his body, or to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98636:12"/>his ſoul: eſpecially ſeing that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality (the Crown of the Bodies perfections) cannot poſſibly be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained here, no more then the certain hour of a mans death can be foreſeen; and that knowledge (which is the prerogative royall of the ſoul) is found but by very few, and that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver abſolutely clear in this life, never but darkened and eclipſed with a multitude of errours. Not to ſpeak of thoſe inferiour and leſſe valuable goods of fortune and the body, health, wealth, &amp;c. the leaſt of which yet being wanting doth infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely diſturb our union with God, and dayly, yea hourly deject us from that ſtate, wherein True Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſiſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>XII.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet notwithſtanding a certain In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choate Felicity (or as 'twere the Firſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98636:13"/>Fruits of happineſſe) may be had in this life.</hi> In the heart of man we may conceive a double reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the appetite it ſelf, or of the motions and ſtirrings of the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite. The former, which is indeed a beginning of happineſſe, a man may, perhaps perfectly, obtain in this life; for it is nothing elſe, but the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining or ſettling of our deſire up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that object, which is in Truth our laſt end. 'Tis true, in a generall notion all men do naturally deſire to be happy (becauſe 'tis naturall for every thing to deſire at leaſt that perfection which is proper to his kind,) yet in particular, or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to their indeavours or motions to attain happineſſe, they do as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally miſtake, few of them know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where to find it, or in what Thing it conſiſts: and therefore we ſee their deſires thereof are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unequall, irregular, and reſtleſſe.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98636:13"/>But when once a man hath found, that his happineſſe conſiſteth in the Contemplation or knowledge of God, and is reſolved to make it his chief buſineſs, ſtudy, and care to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance himſelf therein, his appetite becomes in that reſpect <hi>ſatisfied and quiet:</hi> But yet again, becauſe this knowledge of God is not perfect in this life, but rather in continuall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement towards perfection; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſay in that ſecond ſenſe, that the appetite is <hi>not ſatisfied,</hi> that is to ſay, not the motions and ſtirrings thereof, which indeed never ceaſe, but are continually labouring and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring after greater perfection in that Contemplation; and this ſo much the more inceſſantly and ſtrongly, by how much a man comes nearer to perfect Beatitude, and receives, as it were beforehand, ſome glimpſes and Irradiations thereof. And this is that we call <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98636:14"/>Inchoate</hi> or in its Firſt-fruits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>XIII.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Chriſtians have this Felicity Inchoate in a greater meaſure, then the beſt of Philoſophers.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe the Contemplation and Fruition of God, which good Chriſtians have, are in themſelves greater and more perfect, then thoſe which the moſt excellent Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers could ever arrive unto. By what I have elſewhere ſaid, it is manifeſt, that a Chriſtians life is not founded upon any naturall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple either within or without man, but in ſomething ſupernaturall, that is to ſay, in the Grace of God, by which alſo he is elevated unto a participation of the Divine nature. Seeing therefore that the operation of every thing followeth its Eſſence, (for every thing worketh, ſo far as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98636:14"/>it can, agreeably to its own nature) by how much the nature or eſſence of any thing is more perfect, by ſo much perfecter alſo is it in its opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or working: But Grace is a thing of a much nobler and more perfect eſſence then nature; and therefore the operations or effects w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> proceed from thence, muſt needs excell thoſe of nature. And ſeeing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain that by how much the operation or Action of any Thing is more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, by ſo much a greater and more perfect delight is conceived there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, it muſt needs follow, that thoſe ſpirituall Contentments and Guſts which good Chriſtians have with God, and in God, do infinitely excel thoſe of philoſophers, which a beſt are but naturall, and ſuch as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple is from whence they proceed. Beſides, ſeeing that happineſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in the Contemplation of God, the greater knowledge a man hath
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98636:15"/>of God, the greater, that is, the more perfect is his Contemplation and Fruition of him: But this is certain that Chriſtians have greater know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, then philoſophers; as well in regard of the light of Grace, which perfects that of nature, and reveals unto Chriſtians many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent myſteries altogether unknown to philoſophers; as alſo in regard of that Purity of heart, which, as we have ſhewed elſwhere, true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do injoy in a more excellent meaſure then others: The delights therefore which Chriſtians injoy in their Contemplation of God are much greater in themſelves and more perfect, then thoſe which the beſt of philoſophers could have. And ſeeing that this <hi>happineſſe Inchoate,</hi> which we ſpeak of, doth conſiſt in that Contemplation and Fruition of God which is attainable in this life, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that it is more perfectly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98636:15"/>by Chriſtians then philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers. Laſtly, this <hi>happineſſe Incho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate</hi> is ſo much greater and more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, by how much it cometh nearer to Felicity conſummate, or that of the next life: But the Felicity of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which is here begun, cometh much nearer to Felicity Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, then that of philoſophers; for as much as no man ſhall ever actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally attain heaven but by Grace, (which the philoſophers neither had nor knew;) it is manifeſt therefore, that true Chriſtians are more juſtly eſteemed happy in this world, then philoſophers: and if then they much more then any other ſort of men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>XIIII</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat the delights which good Chriſtians find in the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of God, do ſurpaſſe all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of this world, whither ſenſitive or intellectuall.</hi> Three things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98636:16"/>concurre to the cauſing of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, Firſt the object, or preſence of ſome good; Secondly the ſubject or Thing whereto that good is preſent; Thirdly the union or Conjunction of theſe Two together, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes accompanied with ſome knowledge or reflexion of the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon its proper Act; as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in delights of the taſt, there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired ſome pleaſant meat perhaps or ſuch like thing, Secondly the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan or ſubject of taſt rightly diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Thirdly union of theſe, that is, application of meat to the palate, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with attention of the mind to what is done; for indeed without this nothing is done: For ſhould the meat be never ſo delicious in it ſelf, yet if it were put into the mouth of a man aſleep, certainly he would be little affected with it, for no ſenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would be. We are therefore in the firſt place to obſerve, that the Good
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98636:16"/>which delighteth us, the perfecter it is in it ſelf, the greater delight it cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: now 'tis certain, that Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall natures are much more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, then things ſenſitive; and that the firſt verity is infinitely more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect then all the reſt: it is therefore moſt able and ſit to cauſe the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt delectations. We are to obſerve in the ſecond place, that the faculty likewiſe, by how much <hi>it</hi> is more exquiſite and perfect, ſo much the greater delectation is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceived in the work thereof: for the quality of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light follows immediately that of operation; therefore the more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect operation is, the perfecter is the delight; but as we ſaid, the perfecter the faculty be, the perfecter is alſo the operation: now of the ſame facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that is to be accounted the more perfect operation, which doth more perfectly comprehend and reach its object. Seeing therefore the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98636:17"/>is a more exquiſite faculty then ſenſe, the operation therof muſt needs be more perfect then that of ſenſe, and conſequently a greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light muſt be had in the Acts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then in the Acts of ſenſe. But now among all the Acts which the underſtanding exerciſeth, incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the moſt perfect is the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the firſt verity; in that Contemplation therefore the moſt perfect delight is found. Thirdly, we are to conſider, that the nearer or more intimate the union of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and faculty is, the greater alſo in that reſpect is the delight; But the object of the underſtanding is far more intimately united unto the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty Intellective, then the object of ſenſe is to the ſenſe; for alwayes ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things do more ſtrongly and vehemently unite, then corporall, and eſpecially God, or the firſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whoſe union with all things is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98636:17"/>inexplicably intimate; therefore of neceſſity by the union of God unto the underſtanding that is, by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of God the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light is obtained. We ſee therefore both in regard of the nature and perfection of the object it ſelf, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the faculty, and union of both, that the delights which follow the Act of the underſtanding do infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excell thoſe which follow the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of ſenſe, and that thoſe which follow upon the Contemplation of God Almighty are incomparably greateſt of all. Now ſeeing that God is more perfectly underſtood by Chriſtians, then by any other ſort of men, yea then by the moſt excellent philoſophers themſelves, as before we have ſhewen; and that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall light of their underſtanding is by the light of grace infinitely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and that the union of God with the ſoul, and of the ſoul with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98636:18"/>God through the means of Grace is the moſt admirable of all unions, it follows, as we ſaid, as well from the nature of the object it ſelf, as of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty &amp; union both, that the delights, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> Chriſtians have in the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of God, do infinitely ſurpaſſe the delights of this world not onely ſenſitive but Intellectuall alſo. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, ſeeing that in every particular ſort of Things there may be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome one that is chief, principall, and moſt excellent in that kind, and as it were the meaſure and rule of the reſt, by approximation whereunto the reſt are judged to be more or leſs perfect in that kind; as for example, in the Claſſis or praedicament of hot Things Fire is reconed to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, and as it were the ſtandard of all other heats, every thing being judged to be ſo much the hotter, by how much it cometh nearer to the degree of fire: ſeeing therefore that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98636:18"/>God Almighty in the order of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and Glorious objects is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably ſupreme and more excellent then all others; Thoſe Things which approach neareſt to the perfections of God, or are moſt like him, muſt needs be not onely more perfect in themſelves, but alſo more capable of the moſt raviſhing contentments: but 'tis certain that the u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derſtanding of man or his Intellective part, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nearer unto a likeneſſe with the divine nature then the ſenſitive, and therefore the delights of that muſt be greater then thoſe of ſenſe; and ſeeing that the ſoul of a Chriſtian by means of Grace &amp; other ſupernaturall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges beſtowed on her, comes near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er unto God, then any other which is not in Grace, as is manifeſt by what we have elſwhere ſaid, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that the True Chriſtian doth more participate of divine pleaſures then any man whatſoever. But this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98636:19"/>is to be underſtood principally of perfect Chriſtians: for we confeſſe ſuch as be imperfect do meet with many impediments, by which their Contemplation of Divine Things is obſtructed and troubled, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the delights, wch otherwiſe they might receive, and which perfect men certainly do receive in ſuch Contemplations, ſometimes is utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſt, alwayes much abated: yet not withſtanding even that very little, which they do receive, through the fervour of Charity or divine Love, becomes ſo ſweet and pleaſant to them, that for it alone they do abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely deſpiſe all the contentments of this world, ſaying with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Better is one day in thy Courts, then a Thouſand elſwhere.</hi> Whence alſo it follows, that ſeeing all true Chriſtians more or leſſe do a void the pleaſures of this world, and with ſtudious affection at leaſt pretend
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98636:19"/>unto divine Contemplation, yea even when their taſt and feelings of God are but yet imperfect; it follows, I ſay, that the leaſt delight proceeding in this manner from God doth infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely ſurpaſſe the greateſt of the world, according as one ſervant of God hath told us in the name of all the reſt: <hi>my ſoul</hi> ſaith he upon a time, <hi>refuſed to be comforted: I did but think upon God; and I was drowned in delight.</hi> And although this may ſeem incredible to carnall men, yet we ought not to wonder, for ſuch have not the taſt of the ſpirit. But <hi>be waſhed, O ye ſinners, and make you clean: Away with your evil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſes; ceaſe to do perverſly, learn to do well Come, diſprove me if you can: or, if you cannot; Confeſſe, that the things which we preach unto you are True.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98636:20"/>
               <head>The <hi>XV.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat Chriſtians in the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of Chriſt crucified alſo do find ineſtimable delectations.</hi> We come to the knowledge of Inviſible things in this life by the means of things viſible; becauſe, as philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy teacheth, our underſtanding na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally follows the phantaſie, that is, apprehends nothing, but what is prepared, as it were, and offered to her from thence. Now there is no viſible object in the world which can more effectually lead us unto the knowledge and contemplation of divine things, then the Conſideration of Chriſt crucified proceeding from a lively Faith. Becauſe indeed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can more effectually declare the goodneſſe and ineſtimable cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of God towards man. For ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>to be loved</hi> is a thing of it
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98636:20"/>ſelf very agreeable to nature, <hi>to be beloved</hi> in this manner of God, that is, unto ſo high a pitch, that he ſhould vouchſaſe to be crucified himſelf for us, who can think, but that it is a pleaſure of all pleaſures to conceive? Now ſuch a love of God towards us, doth the conſideration of Chriſt crucified preſent unto our minds, and therefore of neceſſity muſt cauſe in them ineffable dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations. Beſides, hope of Good is a thing which naturally cauſeth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, as making in ſome ſort the good we hope for, preſent to us: and the greater and more certain the good is which we hope, ſo much the greater and more perfect delight is cauſed: But there can be no great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er good imagined, then that which Chriſtians hope for by the Paſſion; nor more certain, for as much as they are aſſured thereof by God himſelf, who for that intent, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98636:21"/>that he might make it ſure to them, was Crucified: Therefore from ſuch hope, ſo great, ſo ſure, Chriſtians cannot but receive ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Conſolation. Thirdly, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is naturally accompanied with delight, for as much as he which wonders at any thing is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly poſſeſſed alſo with ſome great deſire and hope to know what the matter is, at which he finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to wonder. Now what more admirable, yea aſtoniſhing, then that God Almighty ſhould be made man, and dye upon a Gibbet to ſave men? Seeing therefore that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the Contemplation of Chriſts Paſſion do conſider this, and alſo conceive moſt firm hope, to attain one day unto an abſolute aſſurance and ſight of ſo rare a myſtery, how can they be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe affected then with exceſſe of delight? Fourthly, ſeeing God
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98636:21"/>Almighty is ſo infinitely perfect and great, it was not poſſible, that by any one creature he could be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petently expreſſed, but it ſeemed neceſſary to his Divine wiſdome to create an Univerſe of Creatures, that is, this whole world, in the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and variety whereof the Spirit of man might have ſcope enough, and find infinite examples, wherein to contemplate, even unto raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſingularities of his perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And ſeeing in like manner that the goodneſſe of the ſame God our bleſſed Saviour doth as infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurpaſſe all humane underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not one onely, or ſome few, but a million, a numberleſſe multitude, of divine, gracious, and ſtupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous works were requiſite by him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be done; but to expreſſe it in ſome part, in the meditation of which our ſouls are fed, yea glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as it were, with admiration and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98636:22"/>content: Amongſt which none bearing more lively or legible Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of his Love, then that of his Paſſion; it follows that in his Paſſion, and the Contemplation thereof, greateſt content muſt be found: as experience alſo proveth in an infinite number of Chriſtians, who by their actions have more then ſufficiently ſhewen the ſenſe they have had of the Croſſe of our Saviour. It were an endleſſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to go about to expreſſe them, the infinite variety, the multitude and exceſſe of thoſe joyes, which the ſervants of God have taſted from time to time, and do daily taſte in this kind: The lives, yea, the deaths of thoſe antient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans do abundantly teſtifie how great they were; who in infinite multitudes of both ſexes, and of all Conditions, men and women, for the name and for the love of this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98636:22"/>crucified Jeſus, not onely patiently endured all ſorts of perſecutions and affliction, but even exulted and leapt for joy in the midſt of their tortures, dying rather through the extremity of their delights, then pain. The number of Monks and other ſolitary perſons is infinite, who in all times for the love of Jeſus have withdrawn themſelves from the world, and made choice to live in wilderneſſes and caves of the earth, poor, naked, deſtitute of all things, ſave the comforts of divine Love, onely to attend unto this Contemplation. Laſtly the learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Doctours, and wiſeſt men of the world, how often have they aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned not onely the pleaſures and vanities of the world, (which were ſcarce worthy of them) but even their moſt pleaſing and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable Studies, yea their own ſelves alſo, for the love and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of this Jeſus?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:98636:23"/>
               <head>The <hi>XVI</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat the holy Scriptures do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly elevate the mind of good Chriſtians unto theſe Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations.</hi> Firſt, becauſe All Scripture generally doth relate unto Chriſt crucified, according to that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. <hi>The end</hi> or ſcope <hi>of the law is Chriſt.</hi> And for as much as writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in its own nature, is but the ſign of words ſpoken, as ſpeech is of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions or thoughts; becauſe our thoughts do alwayes proceed from ſome interiour light or Illuſtration of the mind, by how much that light is greater and more excellent, ſo much the greater alſo and more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect muſt the Conceptions be, and the ſpeech conſequently more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull, and the writing, wherein that ſpeech is repreſented more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable and profound. Now light
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98636:23"/>ſupernaturall is alwayes greater and more perfect then naturall; And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo that there be ſeverall degrees in that light, it cannot be doubted, but the Prophets, Apoſtles and Evangeliſts, had the greateſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures thereof, as being the men whom Almighty God was pleaſed ſo ſingularly to Illuminate, as that neither in writing nor preaching they could ſo miſtake, as to deliver falſehood for truth: Therfore alſo were their meditations, their ſpeech and all expreſſions of themſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes profound, powerfull, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: He therefore that preſumeth to underſtand their writings without ſupernaturall Illuſtration, is as wiſe as he that would have a bird to fly without wings: of which ſort yet there are ſome in the world, viz. cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Philoſophers, Rhetoricians, Grammarians, Poets of this age, who not knowing or not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98636:24"/>the profundity of ſacred Scriptures, do venture upon them with the ſame temerity, as they do upon <hi>Tully, Hortenſius</hi> or ſome other of their windy Authours; and perhaps not finding in them thoſe flaſhes of elegance, or ſubtilty, to which themſelves are accuſtomed, preſently they fall to flight and think meanly of them, imagining (weak men) nothing to be ſo ſublime as <hi>Plato</hi>'s Philoſophy, no eloquence comparable to ſome piece of <hi>Cicero.</hi> But <hi>he which dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in heaven, ſhall</hi> (one day) <hi>laugh theſe men to ſcorn, yea our Lord ſhall have them in deriſion. For</hi> indeed, <hi>the naturall man perceiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they ſeem fooliſhneſſe unto him, neither can he underſtand them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> But the true Chriſtian, the man that hath ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall light in him, ſhall diſcern
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98636:24"/>them: and if with pure intention and an humble heart he ſet himſelf to the reading of holy Scriptures, meditating or conſidering well what he reades, and begging the grace of divine illumination, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and perſeverance, from God; This man, I ſay, ſhall doubtleſſe be wonderfully elevated by reading, and fitted for divine favours, and ſhall find thoſe endleſſe and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall pleaſures in them, which do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably exceed the greateſt of this world. For this is certain, every Thing is beſt delighted with that which is connaturall unto it, as dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent humours do alwayes affect different recreations, according to that of the Poet —
<q>
                     <l>—Trahit ſua quemque voluptas.</l>
                     <l>Every man hath his own fancy.</l>
                  </q> But unto him that is indued with ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall light, the moſt naturall, that is, moſt agreeable ſtudy of all is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98636:25"/>the ſtudy of holy Scriptures, which proceeded from that ſame fountain of light. Therefore alſo in the reading and contemplation of them the true Chriſtian finds his greateſt content. Beſides, every Thing is beſt pleaſed in ſuch kind of Action as is moſt proper for it ſelf; But there is nothing more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for a Chriſtian then the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of Chriſt crucified by the ſtudy of Scripture: For ſhould he go about to conceive or meditate of him meerly according to naturall reaſon, or the principles of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, neglecting Scripture, he would certainly find leſſe proficiency, and perhaps run himſelf into ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of dangerous errour: for ſuch contemplation were purely naturall, imperfect, and by which he ſhould never attain unto the myſteries of Faith: of which thing we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in our modern Divines,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98636:25"/>who ſeeming to give themſelveꝰ wholly to Ariſtotle and the ſtudy of Philoſophy are become generally leſſe devout, leſſe Contemplatiue then the meaneſt of the people. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; Truth which is the object of underſtanding, the higher it is the greater delight it cauſeth in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition; now the verityes of holy Scripture are the moſt high and myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terious of all other, becauſe they treat principally of ſuch things as be undiſcernable by naturall light. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in regard of the inconſtancy of mans nature, which is neuer long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with the ſame thing, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes affects variety and change of pleaſure, the ſacred Scriptures do become a moſt agreeable exerciſe to our ſpirit. For how admirable, how raviſhing is that variety we meet with in them, of Hiſtories, of ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, of Types, of Figures? and yet a moſt exquiſite harmony between
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98636:26"/>them all, All the parts, All the Books of the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, exactly conſenting in one, and pointing unto the ſame generall and ſupream verity or end, which is the love of God and our neighbour: of which while they treat ſometime hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorically and plainly, ſometime more myſtically and profoundly, they do as it were, preſent a noſe-gay of celeſtiall and various flowers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſoul, which continually chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, do yet moſt conſtantly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe ſpirituall content: We con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therefore, that in the reading and meditation of holy Scripture moſt exquiſite delights be found.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:98636:26"/>
               <head>The <hi>XVII.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat a good Chriſtian, the more ſimply, that is to ſay, ſincerely he liveth, the greater conſolation he hath from God, from our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and from the ſtudy of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures.</hi> This is true, whither we ſpeak of ſimplicity only Interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, or that of the heart: for the underſtanding or mind of man to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his affections, the more pure and ſincere they be, ſo much the more do they render him fit and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of divine Illuſtrations: For this ſimplicity of heart doth indeed require that we be altogether pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from terrene and groſſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to the end that a mans ſpirit might be intirely ſet upon God, and by this ſimplicity or purity, as much as may be, made like unto him. It is true alſo, in regard of ſimplicity
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98636:27"/>exteriour, or that which conſiſteth in the Actions and converſation of men, as is manifeſt: For to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template well divine myſteries, it is neceſſary that the heart of man be in great reſt, and very well compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in it ſelf: and therefore we ſee commonly, that thoſe who deſire to partake of divine Illuminations, do retire themſelves, as much as may be, from the noyſe and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances of the world, as of the Spouſe in the Canticles it is ſaid, <hi>I will lead her into the wilderneſſe,</hi> ſaith he, that is, into ſolitude, and <hi>there will I ſpeak to her heart.</hi> And in an other place, <hi>He ſhall ſit alone, and keep ſilence becauſe,</hi> by ſo doing, <hi>he ſhall be lifted up above himſelf.</hi> And contrariwiſe we ſee, the richer a man is, and more incombred with worldly affairs, the leſſe is he affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted unto contemplation; but where a mans outward affairs are few or
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98636:27"/>none, there is alwayes leſſe diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of mind. Therefore our holy Fathers and predeceſſours in the Contemplative life, were alwayes wont to renounce their affairs of the world, and retire themſelves into Solitude, thereby more promptly and readily to attend Divine Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations. Every man therefore in his particular degree and quality ſhall find, the more ſimply and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly he indeavours to live, the greater Conſolations he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from God and from Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>XVIII.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat the Chriſtian life is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bleſſed life.</hi> Never was there, nor ever ſhall be found out any kind of life more happy then that, becauſe none better. If therefore the life of any men may be accounted happy in this world, it is certainly that of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98636:28"/>Chriſtians. For if we obſerve, it comprehendeth all thoſe perfections, wherein the Philoſophers antiently placed happineſſe, and ſo hath what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they judged good and deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: as for example, if we place happineſſe, as ſome of them did, in the Contemplation of God and things Divine, there is none more excellent and perfect then thoſe which the Chriſtian life affordeth. If we place it in morall virtue, and in the life active, that is, in good government of our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, there is no better to be deſired by man, then that which Chriſtian Philoſophy preſcribeth. If we place it in riches, honours, powers, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or other goods of the body, (though this may ſeem hardeſt) yet the Chriſtian life is not altogether uncapable of theſe, and hath no abſolute repugnance to them: for we ſay, Whatſoever perfection ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98636:28"/>in the effect, is ſome way or other in the cauſe; as the Sunne, which cauſeth heat in all inferiour bodies, is it ſelf alſo, at leaſt virtual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hot: it is not indeed neceſſary, the cauſe ſhould contain every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perfection of the effect for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally and in the ſame manner as the effect doth; it ſufficeth, that it be contained <hi>eminently,</hi> as we ſay, or by ſome more excellent way, then it is in the effect. So in proportion we alſo ſay, that the Chriſtian life doth comprehend, yea afford all thoſe goods which Secular men do ſo much deſire, though not in ſuch manner as they commonly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and hunt after them, but in a better, that is, in a due and congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſubordination of them unto ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour goods. For the Chriſtian life, being as it is a life of wiſdome, a life of moſt perfect prudence and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, when we ſee that the things
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98636:29"/>which the world ſo much admireth, riches, honours, pleaſures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are by them (<hi>viz.</hi> good Chriſtians) in a manner neglected, we cannot but conclude that they find themſelves ſatisfied otherwiſe; that is, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of riches, honours pleaſures <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of a more noble and more excellent nature then thoſe be, which they ſeem to deſpiſe. For having the grace of God, and our Saviour Chriſt himſelf <hi>dwelling in them by Faith,</hi> they conceive themſelves thereby in poſſeſſion of ſo great a good, that in compariſon thereof, there is little elſe worthy of their deſires. They have alſo hereby an aſſured hope to recover in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, whatſoever Beauty or other ornaments of the body, here they might ſeem to want, yea in that degree of excellency and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which the heart of man cannot now conceive, and to injoy with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98636:29"/>Chriſt for ever, that life and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe felicity, of which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. <hi>Eye hath not ſcen, nor the ear heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man to conceive, what Things God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> And hence we obſerve, that good Chriſtians be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of a chearfull and pleaſing Converſation, not ſeeming either to deſire, or to fear any thing over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much in this world, and to be as it were, out of the Gun-ſhot of inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate ſorrow; according as it is written, <hi>Nothing ſhall grieve the Juſt man of whatſoever happeneth unto him;</hi> and as it was ſaid of the Apoſtles of our Saviour, <hi>They went from the Councell rejoycing, that they were held worthy to ſuffer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch for the name of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:98636:30"/>
               <head>The <hi>XIX.</hi> Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat it is no hard matter to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Chriſtian life, and therein by Gods help to perſevere unto the end.</hi> The principall thing required thereto is the <hi>grace of God,</hi> that <hi>grace</hi> I mean, which is not onely a meer gift of God, or <hi>freely given,</hi> but that which maketh a man <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally gracious with God,</hi> or juſt. This indeed is onely to be had from God, but he, through his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite and Immenſe Goodneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ready and inclined to give it unto them that ask, in that reſpect there is no difficulty to attain Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian life. <hi>For if he ſpared not his own ſonne,</hi> as the Apoſtle argueth, <hi>but delivered him up for us all, how ſhall he not with him give us,</hi> and that eaſily, <hi>all Things?</hi> There is alſo required ſome diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98636:30"/>on our part to receive the grace of God, which yet renders not the attaining of Chriſtian life, nor perſeverance therein through Grace, difficult or hard. For can it be hard for a man to do that which is in his own power? Can it be hard for a man to do that which naturall reaſon tells him is beſt, is for his own good, and in his own election? Let a man therefore but obſerue three precepts, and he ſhall find the attaining and perſeverance in Chriſtian life by Gods grace, eaſie. The firſt is, <hi>That he have continuall Thoughts and reflexions upon the miſeries of Humane life, and eſpecially up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hour and iſſues of his death.</hi> For ſeeing that man dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as all other creatures do, he ought often thus to think and reaſon with himſelf; To what purpoſe do I thus labour? What
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98636:31"/>good do all theſe Riches and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours do me? I am ſure to dye and leave them all. I am ſure to dye, yet the hour and time of my death is moſt uncertain. What if I dye to day? as 'tis poſſible enough, what good would it then do me, to have had the whole world at command? Or thus; If the condition of man and beaſt be alike (as in death we ſeem,) truly we men are a great deal more unhappy then they: for unto bruit beaſts Nature it ſelf provideth a convenient food, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient cloathing, houſes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſaries for their life, which we men have not, but with a great deal of labour and pains. Beaſts are ſatisfied with that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which is preſent, never taking care for the future, as man doth, who is never contented with what he hath, but ſtill deſiring inſatiably more, and vexed with a Million
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98636:31"/>of cares for that which is to come. Beaſts are not ſubject to half thoſe infirmities of body which man is, ſickneſſe, weakneſſe, wearineſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and for thoſe of the mind, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, anxieties, diſtreſſes, which we ſuffer in infinite variety every day, they know them not. Beaſts are content with a little, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is preſently ſatisfied with but a ſmall proviſion; but the deſires of man are without end; his heart is reſtleſſe, inſcrutably per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and miſerable with all. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, beaſts have no Thoughts of any future life, nor of the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of Soul, about which men are extreamly perplexed, almoſt in continuall dread and apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of going, after all the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and toylings of this life, unto pains eternall. If therefore our ſoul be not indeed Immortall, there is no creature ſo miſerable
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98636:32"/>as man: But if it be Immortall, then certainly our finall reſt is not here, but muſt be ſought in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life. And ſeeing that it were an abſurd thing to imagine that man, whom both God and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have made the moſt noble and moſt excellent of all other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſhould yet be found to be of them all the moſt miſerable, we muſt confeſſe ſome other happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs reſerved for him, or elſe deny the providence of God over his works. For ſeeing that in the world many Things daily appear new, which were not before, and that nothing can poſſibly make it ſelf, or give Being to it ſelf; it cannot be doubted but that every Thing in the world is made to be, by ſomething elſe which was before it; unleſſe we will be ſuch fools, as to ſay, All things come to paſſe by chance, that is by nothing (for chance is nothing but our
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98636:32"/>ignorance or non-praeviſion of the true cauſe) a paradox ſufficiently confuted by the very order of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, and that wonderfull regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which is obſerved yea ſenſible in all the proceedings of nature. And ſeeing again, that in cauſes ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, we may not run from one to an other <hi>in infinitum,</hi> we muſt pitch at laſt upon ſome one, which ſhall be the firſt and generall cauſe of all; and This is confeſſed to be God: whence alſo we ſee, that without any diſcourſe of Argument, but by meer inſtinct of nature men generally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God, and alſo worſhip him in ſome way or other: nor was there ever man found that could ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in the opinion that <hi>There was no God.</hi> And that God hath providence over the world, the courſe of nature, as we ſaid even now, ſufficiently ſheweth, and the Philoſophers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves confeſſe, ſaying, that <hi>the work
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98636:33"/>of nature is the work of an Intellect which erreth not.</hi> And although it hath come in diſpute among them, whither God hath providence over humane affairs (perhaps in regard of the great irregularities and deviati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which ſeem to be in them, more then in other things) yet certainly it cannot be denied by any wiſe man, but that he hath over them, and over all, and over the leaſt, as much as over the greateſt. Becauſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in every Thing is ſo much the more perfect and more excellent, by how much it further extends it ſelf and taketh care of more Things; ſeeing then that the Providence of God muſt be acknowledged the moſt perfect of all, it muſt alſo of neceſſity extend it ſelf to all Things, it muſt leave nothing unprovided for, it muſt overpaſſe nothing. We obſerve alſo in all cauſes a naturall and vehement inclination, as it were
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98636:33"/>to govern and perfect their effects; as for example, in bruit beaſts, what an admirable and great care have they of their young ones? Seeing therefore that whatſoever good is in the ſecond cauſes, they have it from the firſt, to which they do all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally deſire, ſo much as may be, to aſſimilate themſelves, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that the firſt and generall cauſe of all things (as it were a Common Parent) muſt have a great and exact care over all particular effects, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is the cauſe of all. Beſide, if God hath not providence over hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affairs, what is the reaſon? is it becauſe he cannot? or becauſe he knows not how to govern them? or laſtly becauſe he will not? none of theſe can be imagined of God. For ſhall we think of God, that he cannot, or knoweth not how to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute that, which man both knoweth and alſo is able to do? and if but a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98636:34"/>good man, who hath ability and skill to order affairs is alſo ever wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his own part to do it, ſhall we think of God, who is moſt able, moſt skilfull and wiſe, and alſo inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely good, that he ſhould be leſſe willing? Again, if God Almighty had not care of humane affairs, why hath he given man ſuch a naturall inſtinct and inclination to worſhip him? God and nature, we uſe to ſay, do nothing in vain. We conclude therefore, that it is an argument one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of madneſſe or a diſtempered mind to ſay <hi>There is no God, or that God is, but hath not providence or care over us men;</hi> and that it is the part &amp; duty of a wiſe man not onely to know, but continually to conſider that there is a Governour over the world, who hath the ſame particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar providence over men, that he hath over other naturall Things, that is, to conduct &amp; guide them all by due
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98636:34"/>means unto their proper and laſt ends. And becauſe it is his property to <hi>diſpoſe All Things ſweetly,</hi> he guideth every one of them to their ends in ſuch manne; as is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous and agreeable to their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall natures, and man in particular <hi>Freely</hi> according to that liberty of his will, which is naturall to him. From whence it is alſo, that among men, ſome are good, and ſome are evill: The good are they whoſe life is agreeable to reaſon, conforming themſelves to ſuch Illuminations and Inſpirations as they have from God, in all things ſtudying and endeavouring to pleaſe him: The evill are thoſe who follow not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor obſerve any rectitude or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity of life. If therefore the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty hath providence over humane affairs, and be Juſt, as he is, he muſt certainly have determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with himſelf both to reward
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98636:35"/>the good, and to puniſh ſuch as be evill: But this we ſee not done, at leaſt not exactly, not particularly, in this life, therefore we muſt confeſſe ſome other life to come, wherein the rewards of the Juſt and puniſhments of the wicked ſhall be more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſeen. Which if it be ſo, how much doth it concern us to pleaſe God by a good life? And ſeeing, as we have elſwhere ſhewen, that there can be no better life, then the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an life is, it is to no purpoſe for us to ſeek any where elſe how to live, or how to pleaſe God: for a life ſo led cannot be without its due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, cannot be fruſtrated of that happineſſe which is promiſed to it; if it could, there were no life ſure of happineſſe: for the life of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in many reſpects ſheweth that God hath peculiar providence over them; and therfore if their faith were not true, neither could their life ſo
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98636:35"/>much be governed by it, nor would God ſufter them long in that errour, whoſe Goodneſſe it is to <hi>Illuminate thoſe which are Good and right of heart,</hi> and to harden and leave in blindneſſe onely thoſe which are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. If therefore Theſe Things be ſo, let us believe in Chriſt, and let us live Chriſtianly, for ſo doing, as is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by what hath been ſaid, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not periſh, but muſt be happy in this world and in the next.</p>
               <p>After a man hath by this firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration prepared himſelf, and is reſolved to do what he can to attain Chriſtian life, the ſecond Precept to be given him is this, <hi>viz. That he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider what that thing is, wherein Chriſtian life doth as it were eſſentially conſiſt;</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is the grace of God; I mean that grace, which as we touched before doth juſtifie &amp; make a man good in the ſight of God. For we obſerve ſome men as ſoon as they
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98636:36"/>begin to have a deſire of living Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly, they preſently apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Ceremonies of religion, and performing them exteriourly, they imagine all on the ſudden, that they are become exceeding good Chriſtians: with which vanity ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deceive themſelves, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be Chriſtians, but falſly, being indeed a fooliſh, lukewarm, yet very arrogant ſort of people. Men indeed looking onely on the outſide, praiſe what they ſee, but <hi>God beholds the heart,</hi> and ſayes to theſe men, as our Saviour ſaid to the Phariſees, <hi>ye are they who juſtifie your ſelves before men but God knows your hearts; for</hi> many times <hi>that which is of high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem with men is abomination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</hi> He therefore that deſires in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to live Chriſtianly, let him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour with the utmoſt of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to obtain the grace of God not reſting, til by ſome good ſigns &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98636:36"/>he can probably perſuade himſelf that he hath obtained it. And becauſe the Grace of God is given in and by the Holy Sacraments to all thoſe who devoutly and worthily come unto them, let him prepare himſelf in the ſecond place to receive the Sacraments, with the beſt diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and diligence he can: In par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, If he be a believer, but yet not Baptized, let him prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and come to the Sacrament of Baptiſme, with atrue, ſincere Faith, and good Intention; If he be alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a Chriſtian, but guilty of ſins, let him come with true Contrition, pure Confeſſion, and perfect Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaction, and ſubmit himſelf to the Sacrament of Pennance, and thereby alſo devoutly ſit himſelf for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Euchariſt: and in this courſe let him perſiſt conſtantly, untill by ſome good conjectures he find, that he may have obtained the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98636:37"/>Grace of God. Now the beſt of that ſort, eſpecially for beginners, ſeem to be theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> if he find in himſelf a great and carneſt diſlike of his ſins paſt, and of himſelf for them, a ſerious intention never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to them again, a firm purpoſe to live hereafter according to the law of God, and the duties of that ſtate wherein he is, a delight and taking pleaſure in divine matters, and in doing of good works, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world and of all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, laſtly a longing deſire of the life to come, with a wearineſſe of this preſent. He that by ſuch ſigns as theſe ſhall perceive, that by Gods grace he is become a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, muſt alſo know, that in the way of God, <hi>not to go forward, is to go backward;</hi> and that he onely go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forward, who findeth himſelf to grow daily ſtronger and more fervent in the grace of God, and in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98636:37"/>all virtue: Now this is chieſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by continuall Prayers, as we have ſaid elſewhere, which no man can make rightly, but he that ſtudyeth Simplicity; that is to ſay, Sincerity or purity of heart, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of converſation, together with neglect or renouncing of whatſoever is ſuperſluous. He therefore that deſires to live Chriſtianly according to the duty of that State, wherein he intendeth to fix and ſettle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, muſt be carefull (as we ſay) to live <hi>Simply;</hi> that is, Innocently, Purely, and undiſſemblingly, and in a word, anſwerably in all things to what his profeſſion requireth, ſo as he may be alwayes, as much as poſſible, intent upon Divine and Good Things; I mean, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Service of God by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Meditation, and other Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Religion, or upon the Service of his Neighbour,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98636:38"/>by works of mercy, ſpirituall, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, at home and abroad. But becauſe it is difficult, yea almoſt impoſſible to give inſtructions here, proper for all perſons, by reaſon of the different eſtates and conditions of men, I ſhall adviſe every one, who hath deſire to live indeed this life of a Chriſtian, to addreſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſome good Ghoſtly-Father, who by his learning and experience may be able to direct him; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his counſell to govern himſelf in his ſpirituall affairs. But let him take heed, that he fall not into the hands of theſe luke-warm and indifferent Confeſſours, who have indeed ſome form or ſhew of piety, but renounce the power thereof. It may be thought perhaps very hard to eſcape ſuch perſons, who have outwardly pretenſes of ſanctity, and God onely is the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerner of hearts: Nay whereas it
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98636:38"/>is ſaid, <hi>by their fruits ye ſhall know them,</hi> though they bee indeed but a kind of hypocrites and diſſemblers, yet have they ſome apparence of good works. How then ſhall we know them? I ſay ſtill, it ſhall not be difficult to know them, for any man that deſires to walk uprightly; ſeeing it is written; <hi>Light is ſprung up even in darkneſſe, to the upright in heart.</hi> And in another place, <hi>Your anointing ſhall teach you all things.</hi> And even in naturall things we ſee, thoſe which have different forms can never abſolutely agree, eſpecially if thoſe forms be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: now the form, that is to ſay, the ſpirit and diſpoſition of a true Chriſtian, and of a formaliſt, are as contrary as can be; the one, that is to ſay, the true Chriſtian, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely at the ſervice of God; the other, ever to his own intereſt;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98636:39"/>therefore 'tis impoſſible they ſhould reſemble in all things, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently impoſſible, that the true Chriſtian, who is himſelf zealous for God, and of a right intention, ſhould not diſoern him who is but luke-warm and an hypocrite; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after ſome converſation, and that the <hi>Anointing of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as was ſaid, <hi>Illuminates him.</hi> As ſoon therefore as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that the Father, whom he hath choſen, is one of thoſe who are not as they ſhould be, let him fly from him as he would fly from a Serpent; for as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that walketh with the wiſe ſhall be wiſe; but the friend of fools ſhall become like unto them.</hi> But having found <hi>a good man</hi> indeed, let him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the very ſecrets of his heart to him, let him often and plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe his ſinnes, and according to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98636:39"/>his adviſe let him frequent the holy Communion: for as we have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en elſewhere, amongſt all the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Religion, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Pennance &amp; of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt are moſt efficacious both to cauſe, to augment, and to preſerve Grace. And therefore 'tis the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every good Chriſtian to keep himſelf diligently in eſtate, to frequent thoſe Sacraments with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion.</p>
               <p>After that a man is thus become a Chriſtian, and labours to live Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly, the Third precept I am to give him is This, That <hi>he conſider well, that by many Tribulations we muſt enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> For we ſay in Chriſtian Religion, that <hi>to live well we muſt do good and ſuffer evill, and ſo perſevere unto death.</hi> He therefore that deſires to live like a Chriſtian, muſt prepare
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98636:40"/>and fit himſelf for tribulation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the wiſe man, <hi>My ſonne when thou comeſt to ſerve God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſtand in fear, and prepare thine heart for Temptation;</hi> becauſe adverſity foreſeen doth leſſe trouble us. And that he may more eaſily endure that which comes, let him of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten remember the labours and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Bleſſed Saviour, and of his Saints, as well of the New as the Old Teſtament: let him read fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the hiſtories and lives of the Saints, becauſe, as the Apoſtle faith, <hi>Whatſoever things are written, for our learning they are written, that we by Patience and Conſolation of the Scriptures might have Hope:</hi> let him often, yea continually if it were poſſible, haue before his eyes the ſhortneſſe of this life, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of that which is to come, that is to ſay, the eternity of our glory or
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98636:40"/>pains. For ſeeing nothing can hinder, but that this ſhort life of ours muſt quickly paſſe away, &amp; that at the end of this we muſt of neceſſity arrive at the other, which never ſhall have end, whoſoever ſhall ſeriouſly and duely think of this, will ſurely leſſe regard the troubles of the world; nay, he will think himſelf happy, if by them he can eſcape thoſe eternall pains of hell, and gain heaven though at laſt. He muſt alſo remember, that God Almighty hath prepared moſt excellent rewards for all thoſe who for his Sake, ſuffer temptations and perſecutions here, as it is written, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor the ear heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath it entred into the heart of man, what things God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> He that thinks of this, will not certainly much ſhrink at any temporary tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, but rather be ready to cry
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98636:41"/>out, confeſſing with the Apoſtle, that <hi>the paſſions of this preſent life are not equall to the Glory which is to come, which ſhall be revealed in us by the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> To whom with the Father and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt be aſcribed Glory and Dominion through all ages for ever. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98636:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
